# Estefano Matías Muñoz Moya

PH.D. BIOMECHANICS STUDENT • FARLY STAGE RESEARCHER • DISCABLL ITN MARIE SKADDOWSKA-CURIE ACTION

🗷 estefano.munoz@usach.cl | 🎁 estefano23.github.io | 🖸 0000-0001-5222-4071 | 🖫 Estefano-Munoz-Moya | 🖸 estefano23 | 🛅 estefano-munoz-moya

# Presentation \_\_

Ph.D. student in the Disc4All MSCA-ITN as an early stage researcher (ESR), and Master's degree in Mechanical Engineering. Researchers in biomechanics and biomaterials focused on experimental and numerical work, numerical methods, solid mechanics, finite element method, and continuum mechanics. Responsible, proactive, with excellent learning capacity, empathetic with others, tolerant to failure, and work under pressure.

## **Education**

#### **Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF)**

ra (UPF)

Barcelona, Spain

DOCTORAL DEGREE | IN PROGRESS

• Ph.D. Information and Communication Technologies.

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH) Santiago, Chile

MASTER DEGREE | AWARDED | GPA: 6.9/7.0 | HIGHEST DISTINCTION

M.Sc. Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link

Bachelor Degree | Awarded | GPA: 6.2/7.0

Professional Degree Civil Mechanical Engineering | <u>Diploma Link</u>
 B.Sc. Mechanical Engineering | <u>Diploma Link</u>

# Work Experience \_\_

#### Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH), Departamento de Ingeniería Mecánica (DIMEC)

PART-TIME TEACHER: Engineering Drawing | Theory.

Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021

PART-TIME TEACHER: Strength of Materials | Laboratory.

PART-TIME TEACHER: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering | Theory.

Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021

PART-TIME TEACHER: Computational Mechanical Design | Theory.

Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021

PART-TIME TEACHER: Engineering Drawing | Laboratory.

Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021

#### Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (Ci/CC) | Universidad Santo Tomás (UST)

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT PIA-ANID ANILLO ACT 172037 | Ph. D. NELSON A. LAGOS

• Project: Interacting structure and function of ecological, mechanical and mineralogical properties of marine calcifiers: Shell carbonates as sources of bio-inspiration (Carbo-Nat-Lab).

• Experimental and numerical computational research on the shell skeleton structure from the Chilean coast, subjet to climate change scenarios.

#### Lab. de Biomecáncia y Biomateriales (BioMatLab) | Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH)

Santiago, Chile

2021 - **PRESENT** 

2018 - 2020

Santiago, Chile

Santiago, Chile

Oct. 2018 - Jun. 2021

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT FONDECYT 1170608F | PH. D. CLAUDIO M. GARCÍA-HERRERA | PH. D. DIEGO J. CELENTANO

Oct. 2018 - Jun. 2021

Santiago, Chile

Jan. 2017 - Feb. 2017

- Project: Biomechanical Behaviour of Arteries from Chronic Hypoxic Animals: Experiments, Modelling, Numerical Simulation and Validation.
- Biomechanical characterization of arteries to observe adverse effects, such as hypoxia suffered by Chilean mining workers. In collaboration with the veterinary medical center of the University of Chile.

#### Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH), Departamento de Ingeniería Mecánica (DIMEC)

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering.

Mar. 2020 - Sep. 2020

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Strength of Materials.

Mar. 2019 - Aug. 2019

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Applied Mathematics.

Aug. 2018 - Aug. 2019

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Thermal Systems (Thermodynamics II).

Jul. 2017 - Jan. 2019

Teaching assistance and development of educational guides/tests and resources.

# BBVA Bank Santiago, Chile

 $\label{professional practice in the field of tribological maintenance.} \\$ 

· Maintenance of buildings and power generators of the bank.

# **Publications | Accepted / Under Review / In Progress**

UNDER REVIEW | SCIENTIFIC REPORTS

First Author | 2021

• Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Nelson A. Lagos, Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Antonio G. Checa, Elizabeth M. Harper. Biomechanical behavior of mussel shells: degradation during remodeling, symmetry, and homogeneity of the mechanical properties.

In Progress Second Author | 2021

Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Matías Pacheco-Alarcón, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Diego J. Celentano, Nelson A. Lagos, Marco A. Lardies. Biomechanical characterization of scallop shells exposed to ocean acidification and warming.

In Progress First Author | 2021

• Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Matías Pacheco-Alarcón, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Nelson A. Lagos, Antonio G. Checa. Numerical simulation of *Perumytilus purpuratus* shell strength under predation attacks using finite element analysis.

# **Conferences**

#### XL Congreso de Ciencias del Mar, SCHCM

Europe, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

May. 2021

• COMPORTAMIENTO MECÁNICO SIMÉTRICO DE LA RESISTENCIA DE LAS CONCHAS DEL MEJILLÓN PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS.

#### 11° World Biomaterials Congress (WBC 2020), IUSBSE.

Europe, Virtual

INTERNATIONAL | POSTER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK | POSTER LINK

Dec. 2020

MECHANICAL BEHAVIOR SYMMETRY OF MUSSEL SHELLS AND NUMERICAL METHOD FOR BIOMATERIAL ORTHOTROPY DIRECTIONS.

#### 2º Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2020

PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

# Congreso Chileno de Biomecánica y Biomateriales (CBIO 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | ORGANIZER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2020

PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

#### Congreso Internacional de Metalurgia y Materiales (CONAMET 2019), Universidad Austral de Chile.

UACH, Valdivia, Chile

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov 2019

ANÁLISIS DE LA RESPUESTA BIOMECÁNICA DE PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS ANTE ESCENARIOS DE CAMBIO CLIMÁTICO.

# 1° Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2019), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH. Santiago, Chile

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Aug. 2019

MODELOS CONSTITUTIVOS DE CRECIMIENTO APLICADOS A LA CONCHA DEL PERUMYTILUS PUPURATUS.

#### 25° Congress of the European Society of Biomechanics (ESB 2019), TU Wien.

TU Wien, Vienna, Austria

International | 2 Speaker Presentations | Certificate Link

Jul. 2019

- BIOMECHANICAL BEHAVIOUR ON SHELL CHARACTERISTICS (PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS) ALONG THE CHILEAN COAST.
- NUMERICAL ANALYSIS OF THE BIOMECHANICAL RESPONSE OF OYSTER SHELLS SUBJECTED TO CLIMATE CHANGE SCENARIOS.

#### Courses.

#### 5th VPH Summer School: Stratification of patients with complex phenotypes

Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Virtual

TRAINING PROGRAM | STUDENT | CERTIFICATE LINK

Jun. 2021

• Transversal training in in silico medicine. Dictated by BCN MedTech, Virtual Physiological Human Institute (VPHi), and QUAES Foundation.

## Structure, form, and function of calcifying organisms

CIMARQ UNAB, Valparaíso, Chile

POSTGRADUATE COURSE | STUDENT | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2018

• Dictated by the academics Ph. D. Antonio Checa (Universidad de Granada, Spain) and Ph. D. Fabio Labra (Universidad Santo Tomás, Chile).

# **Memberships**

#### European Society of Biomechanics (ESB)

Europe

STUDENT MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Jul. 2020 - **PRESENT** 

• Membership ID: 3263

## STEM Preeschoolar USACH-DIMEC (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics)

Santiago, Chile

MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019 - **PRESENT** 

• Scientific popularization for preschool children with a gender perspective.

# **Science Popularization**

Science Festival - Festival de la Ciencia (FECI of PAR Explora RM Sur Poniente), Universidad de Chile

Science Festival - 10° Feria Científica USACH, Universidad de Santiago de Chile

UCHILE, Virtual

Nov. 2020

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

· Science experiments for children.

USACH, Santiago, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

Exhibition of biomechanical tests for children.

Exhibition - Molluscas, espiral del cambio - CiiCC, Museo de Historia Natural de Valparaíso (MHNV)

MHNV, Valparaíso, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

• Exhibition of the consequences of climate change in the oceans.

PARQUEMET, Santiago, Chile

Exhibition - XII Fiesta de la ciencia y la tecnología (PAR Explora RM Sur Oriente), Universidad de Chile

Oct. 2018

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

• Exhibition of the mechanical properties of the mollusk shells subject to climate change scenarios.

# About me\_

# Full name: Estefano Matías Muñoz Moya

BASIC INFORMATION

- Birth: 23th of September of 1994 | Age: 26 years old
- · Birth place: Santiago, RM, Republic of Chile
- email: estefano.munoz@usach.cl
- · Lenguages: Native Spanish | Advanced English

#### PROGRAMMING LENGUAGES AND SOFTWARE USAGE

- Programming lenguages: : Fortran | Python | Matlab/Octave | C/C++ | HTML |
- Software usage: In-House FEM Softwares | AutoCAD | Solidworks | Ansys | Inventor | Mathcad | Fusion360 | SAM | Latex | Arduino | Ubuntu | EDEM | GiD | InVesalius | Office (Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Project) |

# References \_

Ph. D. Claudio M. García-Herrera | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Mechanical Engineering Department, Associated Professor, and Researcher - University of Santiago de Chile (USACH). email: claudio.garcia@usach.cl

Ph. D. Nelson A. Lagos | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (CiiCC), Associated Professor, and Researcher - Santo Tomás University (UST). email: nlagoss@santotomas.cl

Ph. D. Diego J. Celentano | ResearchGate Link, Associated Professor and Researcher of Mechanical and Metallurgical Engineering Department, Pontifical Catholic University of Chile (PUC Chile). email: dcelentano@ing.puc.cl